this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
si radio brings you relevant detailed
discussions about software engineering
topics at least once a month
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
podcast
[Music]
welcome to another episode of software
engineering radio this episode is well
you could say a continuation of a topic
we already had it was actually in
episode 62 when our guest was already on
se radio and well the guest is Martina
darsky hi Martin
hi Marcus yeah absolutely and the topic
is not surprisingly Scala and what we
want to do in this episode is take a
look at the somewhat more recent
developments and also try to understand
what this big research grant is all
about that went through Twitter and
blogs recently where some people were
actually wondering how it's possible to
work in Switzerland and get money from
the EU actually since I don't know three
or four years the EU in Switzerland have
signed bilateral agreements I think they
signed them before but it takes a long
time until they actually go into effect
part of the agreement is that
essentially the research would be
combined that means this one pays into
the budget of this the whole research
grant and receives money for the grants
in return AHA okay and I must say that's
very very well at that I just looked at
the total number of grants received per
University so EPFL Lausanne is number
two in Europe as after Cambridge oh
thank you ETH Zurich is number four so I
might get more than their shares of
money that they paid but that's good for
them well that would explain the deal
good so let's talk a little bit about
actually I don't exactly know at which
version number Scala was when we did the
last episode I assume that some of the
2.7 and 2.8 language features we haven't
talked about back then so do you want to
give us a quick recap what has changed
what's new into 7 and - 8 - 7 is a long
time ago I think it - 7 we changed some
behind it maybe some small things - 8
was a big step release the main but it
was mostly a clean up paying
back technical depth kind of release
over the two series of releases we saw
that there were some things that didn't
work out quite as well as we had hoped
one was the integration of arrays of
into into into Scala because Java arrays
are very very restricted and we wanted
to make them into full-blown collections
like any other collection type and the
first time we did that in the two-seven
series it's sort of worked but there
were some some parts where we what we
found not really ideal so we saw we set
out to redesign the whole collection
framework not just a race but a lot of
other things as well and put that in
place and that was I think a big step
forward into eight that now we have a a
functional persistent collections
framework that is very uniform in the
sense that it works on all different
collection types and you always stay in
the type I I have done a lot of research
and I think small talk had a collection
framework also very beautiful that's
close to that but then that's a
dynamically typed language in a
statically typed language I haven't seen
that yet and I realize now that because
it's actually very very hard to achieve
okay except for words we did it - it is
the the is the fact that it's so
complicated is that you know is that
inherent in building such a framework or
is it because of you had to integrate it
somehow with Java's arrays and
collections and all that kind of weird
combination stuff there were two
different set of problems so the at
first the first problem is yes it's
inherently very very hard because the
it's just a new dimension collections
that return collections and that always
have to return the same collection you
started with that you achieve all that
without actually duplicating the code in
every collection because that would be
unacceptable you would end up with far
too much code and you would have far too
many opportunities for inconsistencies
that way so that's something new if you
look at let's say plain Java collections
and they don't do that
so you create a reaction
you read from a collection and element
you can update it you can delete it so
that's just plain old crud collections
as never enters the fact that you say
well I want to transform the home
collection mapper function over it
filtered with a predicate and I want to
get that collection of the same type so
if I do that on a set I want to get that
back and set if I do it on a list I want
to get back a list if I do it on a right
I want to get back an array so a small
talk did it very beautifully at the time
and since then I think very very few
collection libraries did it certainly
not C++ certainly not Java and the
reason I believe is that to do that in a
statically typed setting is just very
hard so it's a type system problem right
it's a static type system problem to be
able to express that in a way that
avoids code duplication and there was
the other bundle of problems to say well
how do we clean the integrate sort of
see the old good old Java types like
arrays and strings and things like that
into that framework and then we sort of
used something we already had in Scala
we just didn't use it consequently
enough before so now essentially all the
previous compiler magic is done is gone
sorry and we do this only with with
implicit conversions which is something
that we had in in Scala so it's in a
sense much more it's less magic and more
more systematic and more and more
regular the way we do that I'm very
happy with that
overall anything else worth mentioning
in 2.8 there were I think there was a
1-1 useful changes that we now have
named named parameters and default
parameters and there were a couple of
other small changes that we have package
objects type influence has gotten better
that's about it yeah so what's planned
for 2.9 and 3.0 ok
2.9 is it's close to being released so I
can talk about that and it ends so then
the biggest change into
9 is parallel collection so we take the
collections framework and we make to
give you optionally the the possibility
to interpret all operations in parallel
so that said where previously let's say
you had a map operation that applied a
function to each collection element one
by one now the map can be applied in
parallel or more precisely the
collection fragment has a very very
intricate load balancing and and the
clustering framework where it will try
to essentially have big chunks of things
that can be executed in parallel because
if you have a let's say a list of 10,000
elements and you want to construct
10,000 tasks to execute each element in
parallel that's probably not the
smartest idea because you are any game
you get in parallelism probably will be
eaten up ten times by the overhead of
creating so many tasks right so how does
the framework find out let's say how
many cores or processors or whatever are
available in the underlying execution
framework or execution runtime system to
do this efficiently it it works with for
joining red poles so with that leaves
for joint framework and I don't know the
details but I think there's a way to
find out how many how many processes you
okay so in other words it's the other
frameworks problem to find that out
that's right okay and 3.0 it's probably
sounds like or or will there be two
point nine point one two three four five
years do you have any plans for 3.0 no
not really
so so I expect to get more libraries and
and more I think the focus will be will
continue to be in parallelism
otherwise for 2.10 it's not that not
that clear as they actually call it 2.10
no even that is not clear within point
ten and 3.0 that will be depend a little
bit on how solid how big the Delta is
from to pry now since a lot of that is
essentially exploratory and there's
certainly a number of things with
to try but none of the things I want to
commit to yet okay so what do you think
about the you know the adoption the job
as Java Scala community how do you are
you happy with how it developed or
develops
yes I'm extremely happy how it develops
because it seems that we we get a big
increase in adoption and the increase
comes from programmers that are curious
that are smart that communicate well so
it's a very very friendly community so
my biggest fear was that as we grow that
the let's say the standards of the
community would be diluted which often
happens right you get a big community
than your standard of discourse go down
but that hasn't happened so I'm really
happy that we just have more smart
people in the community and that's
that's a great great fun to interact
with these people and I'm I'm really
really proud to have that community any
any recent big-name projects everybody
knows about Twitter I guess who use
Scala any success stories we have quite
a few so essentially there quite a few
community and consumer Internet
companies so while Twitter of course
there's Foursquare which is 100% lifts
gala this LinkedIn which has a couple of
big projects now in Scala LinkedIn
signaling to Norbert and the usage is
increasing in these companies the other
big big vector is banks where
essentially all the big banks now have
one one scholar project or several
scholar projects so trading companies
banks UBS Credit Suisse Bank of America
and so on and so on even I heard even
the New York Stock Exchange has actually
SCADA in production so so that's another
big big area where where adoption is
quite roughly any idea why it's
specifically the banks I mean is there
any is it just there you know willing to
experiment in the top new stuff or is
there any specific reason well I think
in a lot of industries you always have
this trade-off of not wanting to be the
first wanting to be conservative using
proving technology
and needing to be better than the
competition so typically the areas where
the the the constraint or the the
necessity to be better than the
competition have wrapped more rapid
innovation so internet startups is one
of these areas and at least the
investment part of banks is the other
because you have to differentiate
yourself you have to be smarter you have
to be faster in competition you have to
have a better trading platform all these
things I'm not talking about the
back-office hangout customer data and
things like that there it's it's
probably much slower although I can't
talk about that yet we also have a big
client that is in that field so really
boring payroll stuff that actually is
it's just starting a scallop project but
that's confidential so if you say client
that's probably in connection with your
Scala solutions startup company thing
that's correct yeah yeah so we haven't
talked about that yet do you want to say
two three words or sentences about it
yeah so that's also very exciting so we
are working on a much more stable and
professional set of developer tools we
are expanding our training so we have a
large number of training sessions
currently all over Europe some in the US
will follow and we work on new
middleware components so that's not yet
for public consumption that there will
be some big announcements to come this
year in next year you mentioned
developer tools actually before our
interview I quickly twittered that we
were going to talk and ask people
whether they had any specific questions
and there are two questions came in one
is from Jeff hammer
when will the IDE support improve I
think this is I agree with him that's a
kind of sore topic for for Scala because
you know it's a statically typed
language i des could do a lot of magic
but then the existing IDs aren't really
great
yeah in fact what we did for the company
we call twenty of the companies that had
scallop projects and we're asking them
essentially the same question what what
do you need what what kind of things are
the most important ones in this color
space and ideally support and most
specifically good Eclipse support yes
exactly and far number one I think
actually the IntelliJ IDE is steadily
improving and is quite solid now so I
think that that's not so much the issue
Eclipse is also improving but currently
lags behind
that's that I spend most of my weekend
working on that time and the company
this kind of solutions has now I think
we have four people working on that so
you should see some some significant
improvements very soon that's great I I
recently tried to build an integration
between Scala and EMF so I can do a
bunch of my modeling stuff with Scala
instead of Java and I have to say I
really have to force myself to use the
eclipse caller ID and in IntelliJ it
doesn't help me in that case because I
need it to be a clip space so I'm really
looking forward to that that's right
that in Eclipse is still the most the
most widely used IDE so that's the most
important one that you have a good
equity offering there
another thing that came to my mind just
a couple minutes ago um how about the
dotnet support is that still really
something you follow up on or is it kind
of deprecated no no we start we follow
up we have a project that is continuing
its it's not so easy so there's lots of
things to put in place to do Scala is
now by now already a fairly big language
and libraries all of that has to be
ported to the net dot net is not
sufficiently different from the JVM so
that you have lots of small small
problems and you have to overcome them
all but that's certainly ongoing so I
don't want to give you an estimated time
of arrival but it should be certainly
this year
you know those 2d support that's great
because I think I might have in my
hairstyle who recently twittered when he
was playing with a sharpened Scala that
he would really love to see
either or both of these languages to
actually be both platforms so I see yeah
yeah no certainly that that would be
useful last question about the current
state of Scala that's a question that
came in from our team demurred and that
is what would you have done differently
if you or would would what would you do
differently if you did if you restarted
Scala now what would I do differently
we wouldn't have known more so there's
some that there's some small syntax
things that probably would have changed
I think at some points we went to at the
time when we did Scala we just said well
look we don't want to argue about syntax
the expression syntax and conditionals
and statements you just take it from
from from Java don't want to change I
think overall that has worked well for
us that said I think that that had led
to some irregularities also in Scala so
I'll give you one so for instance in in
an if and in a while coming from Java
you have to write the expressions in
parentheses rightly right if parents
expression right but the we also have
ifs in let's say in Asgard sand pattern
matching so case blah if and then
actually there's no no need to write the
parentheses the syntax is unambiguous
that way so they optional so that's kind
of I mean it's a small thing but it's
kind of you say well why should I write
it once it why should I follow the if
one else's and the other time not so to
be more regular I think the the right
thing would have to be to say well in
scala you write if and then expression
and then you need another token to say
now you at the end of the expression
because you don't have the parentheses
so you're right if then and we didn't do
that at the time because we wanted to do
it exactly like Java so now I think now
a bit more emancipated you can say you
you can say well they're certain like
maybe some niggly things that we could
actually change
like that you mentioned these kinds of
details means that in general you're
quite happy with how it developed yeah
yeah and generally I'm happy how it
developed and I think the the overall
there's not much I would change ok so
one thing I briefly want to talk about
before we go to the to the research
project and that is you recently talked
about or blocked about these Scala
levels you know you know competency
skill level of various people and I
looked at it and it um well I think it's
useful to have something like that you
know such a classification but on the
other hand it shows that I mean you
won't find that for Java right so it
shows that Scala seems to be a
relatively deep I wouldn't call it a big
language but one that needs brains to
work with from a certain you know at a
certain level so you want to talk about
these Scala levels a bit yeah so that
was essentially just - yeah - to clear
things up so the you probably have also
seen on the internet there's a big
debate whether Scala is a complex
language or a simple language that a lot
of most people who have actually never
tried Scala seriously they tend to say
well it's a complex language and a lot
of people who have tried it say no no
that's not true it's a very simple
language so what is it so I think in the
end it's probably both so if you look at
simplicity so for instance there's this
wonderful Kojo environment for learning
programming using Scala and that shows
that it's actually a whole number of a
large number of kids can can can program
it and not with kids at that their kids
from Indian Indian my poor families I
hope something good school and they use
this stuff so that works and I've seen a
lot of kids that pick it up and say well
this is easy no problem but then you see
essentially some type signatures and
they're quite complicated there's a and
if that's the first thing that you see
you say oh my god this is I will never
understand this yeah so the levels was
sort of an attempt to say why how can it
be both and the the reason can be both
is that essentially SCARA is a what we
call a library century
language so what other language is what
almost every other language would do in
the language and in the compiler we
still do in the library so for instance
the complicated type signatures with
implicit definitions and so on that you
have in the collections that would be
the level expert library designer seeing
l3 so the highest level that would in
almost every other language be done in
the language you would say no no that's
too complicated you can't do that in the
library I have to do that I mean the
compiler writer has to give it to you
and then it's pre can't and you can't
change the thing sorry but that's just
all you you're gonna have so be fair
you'd have to combine these expert
library levels with let's say the
internal compiler interpreter in two
interpretations of let's say Perl or
Ruby or closure or whatever and and then
you will see that well that's you don't
judge Perl Ruby or closure by the
complication of the the internal
implementation they wouldn't be fair
right you would say well that's for the
provider of these abstractions to worry
when I use Perl or Python or Ruby or
closure then I don't want to do I have
nothing whatsoever to do we have eternal
compiler stuff in Scala it's all out in
the open because we're library centric
the compiler only provides it pretty
through the base abstractions and all
the rest you can do in the libraries but
that means that there's a lot of things
that look complex that are out in the
open and with my as I tried to sort of
really be more precise and say what do I
think is expert library writer stuff
which certainly most Scala developers
wouldn't need in their lifetimes maybe
and what are other stuffs things which
which I think are easy and profitable to
use from the start and because we had
internally on the mailing list a
discussion about that so there was this
feeling well
it can it's really a sort of a a two
sided language it can look very
complicated when you write the libraries
library abstractions and it can it can
be very very simple it's usually very
very simple when you use it so I just
wanted to fill in the blanks and say
well what is simple what
protected so that you have something to
talk about right I mean what it's an
interesting discussion also
theoretically what a simple language is
it's Lisp simple because it only has
three concepts or is Java simple because
it has a keyword for everything it's
it's not clear what this means even
indeed they're different dimensions of
Smiles yeah one last thing I read about
this dynamic type recently or did I get
something wrong which is kind of a way
of using some dynamic typing within
Scala is that correct yeah that's it's
its motivations pretty much close to
dynamic in c-sharp 4-0 so it's it can be
used for the yourselves but I was the
main motivation is really to give better
interrupts with dynamic languages so the
JVM has a number of dynamic languages
that are very popular like J Ruby or
Python or closure and the the idea was
to get smooth interrupts with those
languages a dynamic type would be useful
because then you can essentially get
imports and services from let's say
JRuby and call the JRuby code without
having to do a lot of reflection and a
lot of casts you just call the method
and it will be the state J Ruby side
will take care to dispatch that to the
right thing so if a class extends or
implements probably a trade dynamic then
if you write something dot something
then the dot something the second one
isn't isn't statically type each act
right is that the idea exactly it's just
translated into so the dynamic try it
has a method called invoke dynamic right
okay sort of the same as the OP code
that's coming in Java 7 but it's a
version of that and when you when you
just go to a normal method call on a
thing that inherits dynamic and the
method doesn't exist so static methods
will take precedence over dynamic ones
then it will be translated into just an
invoke dynamic call with the method name
as a string argument that's funny
because I I remember I kind of was
wishing for that feature in Java while
ago that's a cool to get it likes things
really that does
need compiler support right because it
has to notice that in that special base
class case it shouldn't do any checking
right yeah it's about ten lines of code
isn't that unsatisfying if you put a
class into the libraries but then you
have to hack the compiler to do
something special with that class only
well that's a question that's an
interesting question whether so
essentially these are market rights they
also exist in Java by the waitress in
serializable it's a market oh I know
people parents to know but the question
is do you want to do it that way or I
don't really have some people say well
you should use maybe an annotation
instead if the compiler needs to
interpret it but in that case it was the
the reason was that we really want to
have the the effect take place over
inheritance so you might have dynamic
and then you might have a whole subclass
hierarchy that all inherits dynamic and
to have this dynamic dispatch thing here
okay to do it and the classes in the
standard library so you can in some
sense consider it part of the language
okay so let's talk a little bit about
the research project so I guess the
general context is that you got some
money called a lot of money to do
research and Scala based language
extensions and you know generally for
concurrency right yeah well yeah when we
say language extensions what we mean by
that is really embedded domain-specific
languages for concurrency we don't plan
to extend the scalar language with
concurrent constructs so but we want to
essentially embed domain-specific
languages that have these constructs so
what's the motivation for yep
so I mean it's clear that the the if you
extrapolate these developments in
hardware then actually it's quite
frightening from the software
perspective that
say the number of processor elements
that you will have to double every two
years at least from now on if you
extrapolate that ten times then you say
well that would be a factor of 1,000 so
if we came out with four or eight cores
we will deal with close to 10,000 cores
in ten years so what do we do with them
even if it doesn't come to pass they're
already today a lot of very powerful
processors like GPUs that need a huge
number of threads to be fully fully busy
for instance new for my nvidia GPU needs
24,000 running threads to actually fully
loaded 24,000 that single GPU so the
question is what do you do with that and
right now I think we all close our eyes
a little bit and say well if you're on
the server we just distribute our
connections over more cores we are okay
if you're on the client then well we use
this stuff only for very specific stuff
like graphics and the rest of the
processors will just be idle most of the
time and we can get away with it because
well we haven't done this for so long
but the problem is on the on the
application side on the data side
there's also always an increasing demand
for more compute power and not just for
graphics but for big data for very
precise models for for more and more
refined calculations and there will be a
clash that we say well - to actually do
these things because individual
processors I'm not getting a whole lot
faster anymore you will have to paralyze
more and more things and nobody knows
how to do that so that's the main
problem so you do that then most people
say well yes but we have actors and we
have SDM software transaction memory and
all these goodies they will help us
there and I don't believe that I used to
believe that I don't believe it anymore
the reason is that even though these
things are undeniably very very useful a
huge step ahead from blocks and monitors
in Java so they're all really good but
the problem is that and they will have a
huge role in what I call concurrent
programming so concurrent programming is
when you need to be parallel because the
world is parallel so
get a lot of power collected connections
you get interrupts from events and
things like that you have have to handle
them concurrently so that's hard and we
need the best tools we have and that is
currently actress and STM's are
certainly great tools for that but I
mean listen this problem of using many
cores is different because it says well
what he used to have to run these
calculations they were sequential right
so sequential is orders of magnitude
simpler than concurrent because we don't
have non determinism you don't have dead
logs they don't have races you have
nothing so now I say well to make use of
these cores give up your nice sequential
world and use all these concurrent stuff
and maybe we give you some better
abstractions like STM and actors it
won't fly people will say well no the
most precious resources still programmer
time and they will not make my
application more buggy and harder to
maintain big it by going concurrent just
to get these extra core powers that
won't happen except in very very
specialized applications so what you
need to do is you need to say well I
need to be able to run these sequential
applications in parallel without add the
program I having to worry about
concurrency and that's the difference
between parallelism and concurrency so
parallelism is you write the stuff
essentially in a sequential way and you
do not put in things like actors or SDM
you do not specify what should be run
when that's the job of the compile okay
so as a first step into nine we have
these parallel collections which are
really good that give you really good
speed ups without the program are having
to do anything that I will just say well
useless do these operations in parallel
and the rest the pilot will we'll figure
out how to do that and that works well
for let's say 10 cores maybe 20 cores I
don't know how how much further we can
push that but it won't get to 10,000
cores 20,000 core simply because you
don't have enough collections if you
have enough parallelism in your program
so then the question is why what do you
do how do you get parallelism for ten
thousand threads and the answer is it
has to come from the applications from
the
lots and lots of applications where you
look at the application code you see the
parallelism let's say you do with
there's a project we do with Stanford on
air flow simulation of a scramjet so
hypersonic jet yeah essentially they
simulate the air flow in in the intake
and in the in the jet at a really super
great detail so it's a huge computation
problem and then of course you see if
you follow all these all these air
molecules you see well you have a lot of
power is now the problem is once you map
that into C++ or or any any standard
general-purpose language the parallelism
is lost all you see is are a bunch of
loops and things like that so so the
idea is if you want to recover that
parallelism we have to essentially go to
the domains and have a domain-specific
language that lets people express this
thing at a very very high level so they
would essentially that's my grid and at
these points in the grid I need a higher
resolution than at these other points
and then I have this computation that I
will compute over that Cray so but you
don't want to build dia cells for air
molecule simulation right it should be a
little bit more generic I think but but
then it can't be too generic because
then you don't you can't express the you
know you can't you don't have the right
abstraction level to express that let's
say domain-specific parallelism right so
we're at the middle ground well there is
actually in a DSL for physics simulation
which is called list which is embedded
in SCADA which does precisely these
things so they are pretty so there are
the details for let's say machine
learning optimal for probabilistic
calculation for there would be a great
opportunity for let's say protein
folding trial and simulation these sort
of things so they are essentially broad
areas where yes we do want to want to do
a DSL but you're right because there are
many DSL the question is well you can't
really write them from beginning to end
with a parser with a compiler with an
optimizer with a debugger with an
Eclipse IDE plugin would be way too much
work well that's an interesting
discussion but we shouldn't have it now
yeah so the beauty is that by embedding
it into SCADA most of the work can be
shared and we
so essentially there's a modular
framework that a lot of the elements of
these ESL's can actually be used across
the ESL's every every DSL will have some
form of expression language and since
Escala embedded which we typically say
well that probably is will be this color
expression language and you can share
that and so the tricky bit with that
though to finish off is that if you just
embed them into Scala the normal ways
your better DSL writers essentially
libraries method calls and things like
that right and again your DSL is in the
ends but when the compiler gets to see
it it's just Scala code and the
parallelism is gone oh it's much harder
to recover that yeah so there's actually
a twist to it and to say well what these
diesels do is when you run them they
will not run the code they will not run
the airflow simulation they will do much
less they will just construct a model of
themselves essentially the airflow
program will say well he is here is my
structure that's what I am supposed to
do and then at a at a back end step a
second optimizer would come and say okay
so that's the airflow program I'm
running on this cluster hardware let's
optimize this program on that hardware
but that's a back-end step which is not
this not the center of Scala compiler
Scala compiler essentially only is there
to go from the DSL to its internal
representation which is which is the
best optimization a representation for
optimization so let me try to try to
explain what I've understood you put
Scala code well you put DSL code into a
scholar program if you run it it builds
an abstract syntax tree of its own right
basically okay well an abstract syntax
tree with all kinds of more or less
semantic annotations then then what
happens first this is obviously
translated to well first the Scala
compiler translates this so you can
actually run it so then when you run the
program and this tree your graph is
built then you need something that
transforms and optimizes this graph
exactly and then outputs what that meant
where you run it right it can output
Kuna it can output MPI on casters so
when playing JVM code so here is what I
don't understand or what I maybe I do
understand and I want to ask about it so
it's possible that this running scholar
program creates let's say C code of
course yeah that's possible that's
actually there's a prototype that exists
that does that yeah so you don't so you
don't really so you do embed the the DSL
code into Scala but it doesn't
necessarily run as part of a scholar
program because you can't easily quote
dynamically load a ceii phone into a
running scholar program that's also
right yeah yeah so that that is both of
some limitations to it so usually what
you do is that you in the back end you
have a splitter which says okay this I
can run on our normal byte codes and
this as as other stuff is essentially
CUDA OpenCL and that will run on the GPU
and the compiler will take care of to
move the data back and forth so you
haven't gotten this integrated thing yet
having we have five years to work on it
but that's the idea that we do that
right now we have sort of individual
bits and pieces where we say well yes we
can not to see we came up to CUDA but
but we have to integrate it all into it
into a common thing where we're then
really the the core would be would be
standard SCADA execution on let's say
JVM and the other thing would be just
sent to special-purpose processes right
because I mean that the from my
perspective there are two aspects to
embedded dsls one is the syntactical
embedding so you can as you said reuse
parts of the scala expression language
for example in your own DSL that's right
but then there is the embedding of the
running program like if you think about
rails then the embedded rails DSL
program runs as part of the execution of
the Ruby program in which it is embedded
and that is not necessarily true in your
case right no that's not necessarily
true
that's right that it could could run as
well okay that that's interesting okay
I I could probably discuss about this
for an hour or so but but you shouldn't
do this now I'll send you an email okay
so there is this term polymorphic
embedding that's used as the let's say
pattern for building these deer cells do
you want to say three words about that
yeah so so the point is it comes down to
the spreading so you have an embedded to
yourself so that means essentially you
start off with a scallop program some
parts of it are this DSL let's say it's
a flow simulation but other parts might
not be I mean there might even be
several T cells I might be a
visualization DSL and air flow
simulation DSL and essentially a scatter
program that ties these two together so
the question is which is which how do
you know whether an expression is just a
plain old kind of expression or whether
it should essentially reflect itself and
construct a tree and the way we know is
with the types so essentially the way we
do that is that we have in a DSL we
would have let's say the DVF low-tide
simulation we would have we would
distinguish that we would have the same
syntactic form of expression but it
gives you a different type namely
essentially a DSL pipe DSL so you would
have Spain's colorant and DSL and you
would have Scala floats DSL floats and
so on
what is a DSL int then I mean at runtime
when you run it well it's it's not a
32-bit number it is an expression so at
an ast or in our case and data flow
graph or whatever you choose that when
you run it will return an int okay so
and that's essentially the polymorphic
embedding that we say well you can have
the same form of expressions and
depending on what type you are and the
types get determine essentially you can
just inherit traits and they will fill
in the types they could mean this thing
or this other thing what's nice about it
is that it lets you easily debug the
whole thing so you could say well
nevermind performance right now I just
want to run this as a scholar program
right I just say well DSL and equals
coloring and they're all
thing will be run just as a normal
scallop program and afterwards when I
say well I need the performance I can
actually play games with that and say
well now I want to reinterpret the DSL
and type and say the assailant is really
my data flow graph that when run will
woodruf tournament and then I pass this
whole thing to my back-end processor
that will spit out optimized parallel
code okay but that's that's why we say
it's polymorphic that means it could be
many things you don't you don't burn it
in from the start
what kind of interpretation your
expression will have it could be DSL
thing or could be standard SCARA thing
and then these different DSL things
build different ast Zoar data flow
graphs and then they are translated
differently yeah there would be
translated differently even though
typically the the the data flow graphs
would would all be built on a common
framework yeah to reuse common
optimizations okay so just to make sure
we we me and the listeners really
understand that dere's else you're going
to build are not general-purpose
concurrency expression tiers as like
actors or message-passing or something
like that these are really specific DSS
for specific purposes and what you're
going to do is you kind of built a
couple of examples to prove the approach
not build bunch of you know DSS that
everybody can use that's right okay but
the point is if you really want to use
these 10,000 the course or whatever then
we won't get there with with with
standard no I general abstractions so so
the only way to get there is to
essentially pick domain after domain
after domain and say well I have a way
now to make machine learning code flash
roll is the computation called fire-safe
so so it's not a silver bullet it's
essentially a way to to gradually get
more and more applications to a state
where they can actually use these 10,000
corage and for me that's currently the
best we can do I don't know any other
way how to how we could use that
otherwise completely I mean I absolutely
agree I mean that it's not just true for
concurrency actually to be to all just
you know things like productivity just
becoming more expressive requires
the main orientation and that's what
I've been in some sense working on for
four years with this whole DSL topic and
and so I obviously I think concurrency
is one of these areas where or M let's
say differently if you do air molecule
simulation or or calculations it's not
just the ability to generate highly
performant code that is domain-specific
also the notations might be matrices and
other you know domain-specific
mathematics specific things so using DSL
to express these concisely and then
using a domain-specific back-end to
generate efficient code is clearly the
way to go exactly yeah yeah
so in a way it's - it's a way to reuse
the expertise of of because I mean still
be a lot of expertise required so
somebody has to write these t-cells and
the people who write the DSL have to
have the domain knowledge that is know
exactly what's required on the
simulation side and have to have the
concurrency knowledge they have to know
how to how to map these things
efficiently but the point is you
afterwards after this is done you can
reuse it then the actually physicists or
people using that they don't need to
know about clusters and MPI and orange
anymore they can use the DSL so that's
sort of the promise that you do things
once and then can reuse the very
precious expertise of the people who
know how to paralyze this well right and
since you were talking about silver
bullets the Silver Bullet
if there is one would not be you know
the fact that you now have this
general-purpose DSL which is a kind of
oxymoron in itself anyway but the Silver
Bullet would be the framework and the
infrastructure you were researching to
be able to quickly and easily relatively
quickly and easily build these kinds of
DSL
yeah but like I said I don't think there
is no but that's the that's the advance
you make to make building diaz else more
simple so it becomes practical for many
domains yeah yeah I think I think now we
have a we have a lever to to be able to
push things so I the way I see it
previously we had just no idea how to
use 10,000 cores in in a way that that
was reusable and now we
I have an idea how this might work with
continuous work it's not a silver bullet
at all this means that we have a way to
canalize and organize the the work off
that's still necessary of a lot of
experts in domains and in parallels yeah
last question do you expect that it
requires actual Scala language
extensions to make this work or do you
think this can all be done with the
existing facilities and put into
libraries and and fancy types it will
require not so much extensions but some
slightly interpretation so there's some
small tweaks we have to do to the
language standard which are done we have
a branch essentially for this work that
that's them in an experimental way they
haven't been rolled back into trunk yet
so what it requires is it's actually
very simple
so Scala already lets you reinterpret
plus or times or any operations any
method call any way you like because
well it's just a method call and on your
new types you can reinterpret these
methods any way you like right yeah but
there are a couple of things that are
not in that category so one of them is
if then else if then else is hard-coded
in language it takes a boolean and it
gives you either left expression or that
expression that's a return and India
sells let's say I want to do a DSL that
does continuous evaluation of a signal
so then I want to say well my that it
would make perfect sense to have an
if-then-else which says well for the
periods where essentially my conditional
signal is true I will evaluate my
resulting signal to the den part and
otherwise really evaluate it to the end
part so then the if-then-else wouldn't
take a boolean but a signal of boolean
as its condition right now I can't do
that because they Eastern else is a
heart is a language construct so what we
do in the virtual eye is what we call
language virtualization and in the
virtualization branch what we do is
essentially we take if-then-else and the
we have a couple of remaining construct
so it's while do and for loop know for
loops already virtualized but while
loops and tries and things like that and
we map them
also to method calls that he can
overwrite okay so essentially all we
need to do is free these few remaining
language things which are hard-coded in
the language to say well they are
there's also a way to reinterpret notes
and I we have that you have full
language virtualization and we can do
that I think all that's needed can I ask
you one more last question yes now once
you have this nice high level DSL for
airflow molecule whatever and then then
of course you do have a custom back-end
and you have a custom notation custom in
the sense you know whatever you can do
with Scala is flexible syntax what about
I des I mean do you think about being
able to use some that say meta
programming in the farthest sense to
adapt the IDE so you get domains with
the code completion domain-specific
error messages beyond what you can do
through magic typing because these these
type errors will not be domain-specific
they will say something about types and
nobody gets what it means yeah that's a
very good question
generally for T cells it's a general
problem with embedded DSL that you say
well write me better you get all the
errors in the in the host language and
not the embedded language and and that
that can be a problem because then if
you should this this fancy new embedded
language to attack your physicists and
to say well you use that but if you use
other things it really would help if you
knew Scala as well because that's in the
end of the program and then well maybe
not every physicist will jump at that
and say yes gala was the thing I wanted
to learn anyway for all this time so so
so what do we do that so so I think one
possibility which we want to explore is
to have something like like profiles so
that we one idea would be that we could
at the head of the program say
essentially what language are we talking
about and then we could use our plug-in
architecture of the compiler to say
after the parser after the process is
done we essentially would check whether
the program that's written here actually
conforms to the DSL that was declared
rifle say I want lists then definitely
the checker would actually check that on
you use only lists constructs
and you could push that so far that this
checker that would run before the
general scholar type checker would be so
refined that it would catch all type
errors as well once you do that then you
you know that afterwards essentially
once you get to the real scholar type
checker all this stuff is just for
translation there wouldn't be any errors
anymore right so that would be nice and
I think it's doable it depends how
difficult the typing problems in dsls
are but typically they are much more
simple as typing problems in the base
language then the next question is how
do you do push that into completion and
other BI other IDE features and that's
indeed a very good question and that's
also some of the questions we want to
look at in the research program okay so
I I see it's a we have a problem there
that we wanted wanna solve and it should
be very interesting to think of
solutions because in the end that's the
big advantage of real external DSL right
if you use X text or MPs or intentional
whatever you get a complete IDE for it
and that is appealing but somebody has
to write that yeah I'll get back to you
[Laughter]
okay thank you very much that was very
interesting as an update and an outlook
of what's going to happen Thank You
Marcos it was fun talking good very good
and well have a nice what is it Monday I
have a nice week bye so that's it thanks
everybody for listening and of course
once again thanks to Martine for being
on the show I think this is a very
interesting project and it's also I
really like to hear what he says right I
mean this this statement that you can
only become significantly more efficient
if you become domain-specific is is
clearly aligned with my line of thinking
so great to see that and it's going to
be interesting I mean I've worked a lot
with DSL with various tools and you
probably when you listen to it you heard
me almost say the word MPs right but um
it will be interesting to see how far
they can actually take it and use a
text-only language you know and the
question will be mostly from my
perspective this ability to customize
the IDE anyway I'm certainly going to
follow it fascinating topic and
I hope you found it interesting as well
let us know what you think you can reach
us at team @ SE - radio dotnet and well
that's it bye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio as a radio is an
educational program brought to you by
Xhosa Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team via
the website or you can advertise for SA
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook you can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if your feedback is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details
[Music]